[Applause]
[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer org
slash software this March 21st and 22nd
don't miss technique night in Burlingame
California just minutes from the San
Francisco Airport come to tech ignite to
get rock-solid in phone forecasts on
adaptive cybersecurity emerging
technologies machine learning and deep
learning operational intelligence and
much more join tech superstars Steve
Wozniak and Grady Booch plus sea level
leaders from Netflix Google IBM
Salesforce GE digital and Intel to gain
valuable insights and learn about real
world solutions you can start applying
today register now for the I Triple E
computer society's premier conference
tech ignite at tech ignite computer org
and discover the truth behind technology
hello everyone I'm Finley new for
software engineering radio and I'm here
today with Alexander to Lindner who is a
consultant at crisp he has a decade of
experience in software development but
he's also worked in architecture
management and testing and over the past
few years he's really been getting
interested in test automation and
continuous delivery but the reason I'm
interviewing him today's I just read his
book developer testing hi Alexander
welcome to the show - thanks for having
me so first of all I want to know why
did you write this book because there
are a lot of books about testing already
why did you think there was a need for
another book on testing oh well that's
that's a great question actually I
I've seen many needs so after a while
after having done certain consultancy
thing is I kept bumping into the same
recurring pattern of problems the same
phenomena the same learning curve and I
read a lot myself I used to run a book
review site and so I was quite aware of
the markets and I was aware of the
literary literature back then what
questions it was addressing and I really
did see a gap and the gap was basically
that at least to me there were really
two camps when it comes to written
material one camp was the testing
literature which was very good at
conveying information about testing
techniques but what happened in many of
these books was that they tended to
drift off in the direction of a testing
process and that is something I asked
the developer back then couldn't really
really relate to so so it was focused
too much on the tester and northern the
developer do right yes the tester and
actually not not really that I wouldn't
even go there I'd say some of the books
not not all of them were actually
focusing on just process on on how to
document stuff I - meat was very
intensive
so that's one thing and then we've got
all these like developer books and
they're usually the ones I read usually
had like J unit X unit or something in
the title and again they sort of favor
the tool they were very good at explain
the tool but I what I saw missing was
what actually puts put into this tool
okay you've got this tool running you
know how to write your unit test or
whatever kind of test your writing and
okay so what you're supposed to put in
into this test and then there was
another third camp of books which was
TDD books and this was very interesting
because again at least it was my opinion
that books on test-driven development
days they stopped after having explained
test-driven development as a technique
probably were gonna return to that topic
sometime but again I was missing what to
actually put it in the tests so that's
one angle then the other angle is as I
said I've been working as a consultant
with different clients meeting different
people seeing different organizations
and I've seen recurring patterns of sort
of stages of quality awareness in teams
and these stages usually they usually
involve them developers knowing
something about a unit testing framework
they knew knew something about mock
framework or something and then there
was this gap and there was there was
actually not again I saw that not to too
many people were concerned with what to
put into the their unit tests yeah so
there needs to be a book that explains
people what to test or what tests right
and not really how to write the test and
how to
techniques to test I think that's how I
can summarize for answer well there
needs to be something there is to beat
as a meet in the unit testing what to
what to put in there there and as agile
testing became it became a topic that
also a little added to the confusion
because that sort of stirred the pot a
little and again Lisa and Janet did a
fantastic job with that book but
attacked really stirred the pot and for
a few years people on conferences
testing conferences we were really
talking about okay what are we supposed
to do what the developers do what the
agile teams do so again I wanted to
clarify these these roles okay so that's
maybe clarify that for our listeners a
little bit as well what do you define as
testing because that's not even agreed
upon I think by all people in the
testing space haha and yes and I so wish
I had a super good answer to that I do
have a wish answer like I wish testing
was that and I wish I could define this
but I get let's just explore the things
that you may encounter when you speak
about testing so in certain types of
organizations where I would say people
are having a hard time adapting to
certain practices testing is the magic
things thing that only testers can do no
one else so that is that will be one
answer the schoolbook answer is to
basically execute software to find bugs
that's the schoolbook answer i don't
really like that because it's too narrow
so a better schoolbook answer is
validating and verifying because so now
we're getting somewhere we need to
actually see whether the stuff that
we're supposed to test is actually the
stuff we need it's not not only whether
it's worse correctly or does it actually
have a place in this world so so I like
that validation seeing are we Eve have
we even included the right
schooling requirements does it meet with
expectations does it delight so that
part I like
another thing to put into testing kind
of like its detection and Prevention so
again there's like a temporal aspects in
here testing is obviously the
traditional word is detecting bugs as I
said running software to don't cover
bugs but we need a prevention aspect so
I if you put those two together it's it
sort of a good definition if it were up
to me if I could just wave my magic wand
I would say that I'd like testing to be
about ensuring goodness I mean also
testing is framed from a negative
perspective we want to prevent bugs
which is a negative thing yes but making
goodness is from a positive thing yes I
think that nicely leads on to the next
question already a little bit what is
developer testing what is the difference
between testing in a more traditional
sense when a tester does it and testing
when a developer does it is that the
same thing or are those really different
things with different goals again if
testing is about ensuring goodness or
fitness they obviously have the same
goal because that's a that's a big goal
that being said I just need to inject
this because it's so so funny
when I wrote the book I've been at this
for four or four years sure there have
been some there been kids in between but
it took a while to write the book in the
printed version I actually still didn't
know what developer testing was so
developer I just to give you some
background here the book actually
started as a bunch of good techniques
just this is like if you do this and
this and that and if we combine this
into into one thing it's probably gonna
be good it's probably gonna shown
goodness after having had the book
printed I finally discovered what
developer testing is and developer
testing is so ever I've got this catchy
phrase which I'm trying to repeat and
and sort of reuse and it's it's the
developers intentional and systematic
employment of testing tools and
techniques with the purpose of achieving
the highest possible correctness of the
software that they write and the key
words here are actually intentional and
systematic because that's as opposed to
first of all if you've got the intention
to use tools and techniques you're
obviously going to learn about tools and
techniques you're gonna make some
efforts to to read up on them to explore
new tools and techniques and if you do
this systematically
you're gonna tackle the hard cases
because as I said in the beginning
people do at least when I started
writing the book I so many I used to see
many unit tests which which were or
tests for that matter which were only
targeting the things that were simple
and these also these simple things were
kind of incomplete also so that tests
weren't really that good and that wasn't
systematic so that's what I put
systematic yeah into this definition
can we really expect developers to test
their own code I didn't know if this is
a thing in Swedish or even in English
but in my native language Dutch we have
a scene the butcher approves the meat
which is I mean it doesn't make sense if
someone approves its own products and
it's not necessarily malice it's not
that developers are doing it
intentionally but if I overlook a
certain scenario in programming
how can I still put that scenario I
didn't even think of in a test is this
really possible or is it a wise idea if
someone else checks the meat yes yes
okay so so here we're actually on the
topic on of creator bias and stuff like
stuff like that and if you sort of make
an argument for independent testing this
is kind of the argument you would be
raising as I will explore further
developer testing is a lot about
preventing it's about prevention
so in the ideal world let's say let's
let's say we had an Oracle that would be
able to to tell us exactly what false
scenarios that would appear in the
product so I would rather have that
Oracle sitting next to me and me being
the developer saying okay what are you
going to test what do I need to what do
I need to look for and this is a little
the this effect that I'm looking for so
as a developer you are biased yes there
are many good words for this but at the
same time you need you need to verify
your stuff somehow so first of all the
optional to not doing any developer
testing at all is basically re running
your program is that that's just random
and it's haphazard and it's tedious and
boring so that's that's one extreme if
you don't do any developer testing which
in this case includes unit testing you
need to rerun your program second thing
is as a developer if you think about
testing just thinking about that this
stuff needs to be verified somehow will
affect the design that's not
controversial you you will follow
certain principles when organizing your
code you maybe will make it testable so
that's one thing you will enable future
testability and I don't think there's
any wrong in really doing your best as a
developer you want to check and verify
your code to the best of your ability
and yes your ability will obviously be
biased because it's sort of your child
that you're examining but I think that's
the best option and if you at that point
in time happen to have your Oracle or
your testing buddy actually telling you
I will test for this you can actually
put all these checks in in the code up
front instead of having a tester doing
them so yes there is bias but the
the positive sites so I'll play this
anyway definitely and then this also
relates to the different roles within a
company of testers and developers it
used to be the case I think that there
was a very clear role for a developer
and a clear role for a tester if testing
is moving to developers how does that
influence the job of a tester do they do
different things
well I I'd say that the thing that
actually influences the job of the
tester more is not really where the
testing as such happens it's more they
actually the delivery cadence I think
that's the thing that influences the
testers work obviously if you if you if
you were in the habit of delivering
something let's say on a quarterly basis
or something you as a especially as a
traditional tester would work in a
certain way now if we need to deliver
stuff weekly or bi-weekly or even more
frequently obviously whatever you did to
need to ensure quality in these long
releases has to change so I think that
that is what's actually pushing the
change in the tester role it is actually
the cadence to delivery cadence so the
continuous delivery having your tests
run automatically and deploying every
week is really different from when you
were still burning your software CD and
shipping it yes yes so it's simply
there's simply no way for an agile team
to have a sustainable pace with usually
testers are still still outnumbered in
teams and there's no way to do your even
your regression your fundamental
regression testing so you need
verification to be done order to happen
as a result of developer work because
developer testing I didn't really manage
to squeeze it in upfront here but
developer testing is a lot about freeing
up
testers time because my experience is
that testers are in teams where or where
developers are not very good at testing
or don't do any testing at all what's
going to happen is that the tester will
basically do what people call checking
they're just gonna verify basically just
double check verify what developers do
and that's actually I'd say it's a waste
of time and it's very boring for it's
really challenging because they need to
do testers need to verify stuff over and
over iteration after iteration manually
and this is something that doesn't leave
any room for what I would call high
value testing and also for the developer
that's not a very comfortable situation
because if I make a mistake and the test
tells me immediately I'm in that piece
of code and I can easily fix it whereas
if three weeks later a test or shows up
on my desk saying hey this is wrong I
have to remember what I was doing what
changes I made right that iteration I
think also really supports the developer
and not just the tester right so I heard
that some companies have started doing
something they call the hybrid model
right where the difference between
testers and developments is just gone so
they trained the quality engineers on so
friends and union they trained so for
engineers on testing and everyone does
coding and testing do you think that's a
good idea
well I I haven't really seen this play
out in practice what usually the model
I've seen is the model of let's call
this the school book agile team or scrum
team where everyone is a developer so
that title I mean scrum removes that
title altogether
yeah so everybody is doing product
development not development in the sense
of writing code some days actually miss
the word programmer because it was quite
clear
so the way the teams I've seen usually
we're in situations where testers were
able to pick up on this we're able to
adapt and developers to for that matter
is that as a previous tester you are
still the one who knows most about
quality who knows most about testing
tech testing techniques exploratory
testing non-functional testing this will
still be your domain of expertise but
you will take more interests in the
daily work of the team you will no
longer sort of wait for stuff to appear
at your desk and you're supposed to test
it you you as a tester in such a team
you need to be proactive and that's
that's actually how I would summarize
agile testing so it's more about the
process and the team you think that's
which that hybrid model will impacts
then we need to job or the work you do
every day and be more engaged yes I
think if you phrase it like that I mean
that is what that is the outcome you're
looking for and by a sort of
cross-training people you're hoping for
that effect and in essence that's good
again if developer testing is actually
facilitating this kind of hybrid thing
because it actually really really brings
in testing techniques and shows you how
they are used in your daily development
work so from that point of view
developer testing is really really
cornerstone for for this and again
returning to this short short of
delivering Cage's Cadence's as a tester
if you're not technologically savvy or
at least you you don't need to you were
never supposed to be a super developer
as a tester but you need to understand
about the technology you need to know
the technology stack because different
stacks will have different
characteristics they will be prone to
different kinds of-of thief
and especially since we're the stacks
are getting more and more complicated
there are more moving parts there's more
boilerplate it's kind of hard to be able
to spot root causes of the defects
unless you know where to dig so I think
this becomes more or less inevitable so
I think we can agree that writing unit
tests is programming because that's
writing source code yes
so are there forms of testing that are
not programming are there extra skills
that testers have that aren't
programming as for skills I'd like to
emphasize more the mind sets which can
be a skill I think having a certain
mindset
wow that's that's the deep one let's go
I need to sleep on this I would really
sleep on this one so again I'd like to
speak in terms of roles and if if you
are in the role of the tester you will
obviously do different things you will
work more proactively with you you
basically you will be the one asking the
questions at least to me the tester own
is the inquisitive role in every
situation you're supposed to ask what
could possibly happen here what could go
wrong and there are so many ways stuff
can go wrong again will the users like
this will users like the product have we
explored all the variations of the I
don't like the work requirements but
requirements will they'll be will there
be any security issues will there be any
performance if issues and and this these
are questions you need to be asking
constantly so that's that's the
important thing here yes oh maybe I can
summarize that as the tester ultimately
has the customer as
central central thing in their job they
think we'll the customer like this will
it work will it'll be buggy we're a
developer ultimately has a product
central they are building the product
well actually in a perfect world I would
actually hope that both work towards the
same goal however how this plays out in
practice is that provided that the
developers do the fundamentals like like
developer testing they will be focused
on actually implementing the product and
implementing the code to test the
product whereas in this scenario as a
tester you will have time to not just
double-check what the developers are
doing and you will have time to ask all
these questions yes so in your book you
describe this I think really well
because you describe clearly two
different objectives for testing one
objective you call the critique
objective which is basically and the
developer says it works on my machine
and then the tester or third person
that's in the role of testing is trying
to critique the piece of software where
you also have the support objective of
testing where the testing is supposed to
make programming easier to make turnover
quicker or make it less painful so how
are those two test objectives different
and do you typically have both within a
company or are some companies really the
tests critique path and are orders
really the test support bag can you
elaborate them oh yes I'd love to
so first of all this is sort of borrowed
from the agile testing quadrants of
course Primerica and popularized by Lisa
and Janet's of course but there is this
also includes my favorite Stroman which
is traditional testing so this the
actual situation is my favorite strong
and traditional testing is not able to
sorta fight back if you sort of take
some steps at it so what I wanted to say
with that these priority paragraphs here
is actually first of all I wanted to
highlight this old creepy adversarial
parts of testing this where you sort of
are suspicious you you want to basically
well I I've met some tests let's just
think like that
I meant met some testers who were very
very happy when the developers failed
yeah and that's actually the label they
put on and the developers have failed so
does of course there must be joy in
discovering the effects because you need
to need to be motivated I mean you need
to to be able to leave your bed and go
home
go to work and do stuff that you're
happy about and finding bugs is
something that makes you happy but I
think there's a difference between
finding a defect as in contributing to
the quality of a product versus finding
defects just to see that somebody else
fails yeah it's also really the
difference between of course the
developer and the products if I find a
bug and I want to make the product
better it's really different from saying
you as a person have put in that line of
source code that is wrong that is that's
that's horrible and unfortunately it
says it still happens I wish it hadn't
but it's still bad but I think it's it's
going away this is this a good friend
here but anyway so this critiquing there
are two dimensions of critiquing
supporting again if we just look at the
ad jack Cotton's model which has tests
actually the newer agile testing
quadrants not nowadays call this guide
development it's not support but it says
it's called guy development but and this
this is what developer testing actually
is you need practices you need
techniques that will help your
development which I mean the obvious
case is of course unit testing but
basically any kind of testing or
checking that can be
to mated by by developers is guiding
your development and is supporting but
there's another dimension too and I
think we've touched on this is in you as
a tester your objective is not really to
find flaws your objective is to
contribute to a good product so whatever
you do you do this proactively and you
do this in a supportive manner so that's
testing to support weather testing to
critique in the age of warrants it's
actually just looking for at the product
from from the outside it's basically
evaluating its so it's critiquing but
not criticizing so that in Indian
aquaporins that well what it is at least
I hope it is however what I wanted to
bring into that section particular
sections of the book is that this
critique mindset it just may become too
much and it's again this use you're just
speaking in terms of risk you speak of
distrust you you're actually building on
the false building metaphor for for
software construction when you expect a
good blueprint and you expect that
blueprint being implemented and you see
yourself as a kind of building
construction inspector you want to
examine the shafts the wiring and
hopefully you want to to find something
wrong you want to find these cracks in
the concrete or or something or
something and that's my favorite strong
man actually so suppose you're in a
situation and some of our listeners
might be in a situation where testing is
mainly critiquing mm-hmm how do you move
your organization towards more the
support form of testing which I think
might be more fun environment to work in
a more constructive environment working
is this possible
have you seen in your work as a
consultant organizations make that shift
and if so how
okay so I I had very good news here I
wish I had the simple formula and
syllable
but basically what this is this touches
on the big topic of agile
transformations its touches on the topic
of change management
Nessun yes it's bigger it's a big
mindset shift and you you would use
basically all your skills and tricks in
these two areas to to change a team's
work one thing that usually works
actually or it's sort of a stuff under
all I say is things with other either
bend or break again if you shorten your
Cadence's you need to do stuff
differently and if you adopt if you love
truly agile development where you're not
just sort of dude doing iterative
incremental development you're not just
paying lip service to it but you do
actually have shippable and preferably
ship software often this will force you
into certain working habits there's no
way you can sustain some ways yes
there's no way but but the caveat is
that you really you can sort of play I'm
gonna use scrum as an example you can
play scrum here saying that okay we've
got this we're delivering in six months
but we do have our two-week sprints
because I have not seen that work you
can force this this change by playing
scrum so to say or or any other agile
methodology so that that will drive that
obviously will drive this change
another thing is actually rotations with
within the teams I mean teams are on
paper static but they are dynamics
especially as a consultant I enter and
exit teams and if if the mix of people
changes or formal informal leadership
changes you have your opportunities but
something needs to just talking about it
advocating it I've never seen that
so you have to really be able or be
willing to make changes within your team
within your organization for that change
to work yes or either you need to be
pressed into this again or you need need
to swap out enough people that change
happen so we've been talking a lot about
agile and scrum and testing but in your
book you make another connection between
software craftsmanship and testing so I
love so for craftsmanship and the way I
am the way I see so for craftsmanship is
that it is about emphasizing skills
coding skills of developers you have to
take your self serious your own skill
series and with that you take your
source code serious is that we do you
agree in the definition of software
craftsmanship yes I think the key word
is skills here it's it's it's skills so
I just happen as just happen to have the
craftsmanship manifested with me here
yes I came prepared I don't know how how
I knew and again if I read it it says
not only working software but also
well-crafted software not only
responding to change but also steady
adding value not only individuals and
interactions but also a community of
professionals not only customer
collaboration but also productive
partnerships actually from my point of
view I usually make the connection
between points 1 & 3 which is
well-crafted software and community of
professionals so I think if you just if
you just say what is software
craftsmanship to you these are the two
points that will come up and with this
it comes certain practices I would
mention there are several books on
writing good code Robert Martin's book
clean code is obviously the most famous
one but there are other very good books
we have a few suggestions that you can
share oh I would so love to - although I
don't really
I've got them yeah I've got them on my
review site actually I just they slipped
my mind
there's actually one very good it just
stick around sorry yeah
searching for a new job is stressful and
scary then you go through the interview
process only to find the salary offer or
company culture doesn't match what
you're looking for
hired calm is the world's most
intelligent talent matching platform for
engineering we make your job search
faster and stress-free
after completing the application top
employers apply to hire you you receive
personalized interview requests and
upfront salary information your
dedicated advocate will assist you
providing career coaching to help you
with potential employers hired calm
hides your profile from current and past
employers to respect your privacy the
best part it's always free today is se
Radio listeners can earn a $2,000 hiring
bonus by signing up at hire calm / se
radio find your next chapter at hired
comm / se so how is so far craftsmanship
related to testing or to developer
testing okay so developer testing will
thrive if there's an underlying
technical excellence because what what I
would put into software craftsmanship is
again just clink of this one thing
refactoring is another big thing that
you need to do and there are certain
principles it's at least it's just me
putting them in the bag of something
craftsmanship is this like command core
separation following the law of Demeter
and stuff like that and all of this is
sort of pursuing this actively learning
about this stuff and making your code
align with this stuff is SAP software
craftsmanship to me and reaching out to
other people who obviously won't want to
say at least that's affirmed
craftsmanship to me and of course it's
it's easier if you've got this objective
it's it's not a very big step to take to
say okay we have well crafted
now we need to see that our well-crafted
code actually works and we'll keep
working iteration after iteration so in
that sense the step is small yes however
there's a but there's a but here and I
think you can probably know I haven't
spent too much time thinking about this
but I think you can have an well crafted
code which is not very testable hmm
which is or III need to construct some
example I haven't really thought about
this but but I think it's not the one
one-to-one mapping actually is yes I
can't I can't make the promise actually
maybe this will be my homework I don't
know so maybe I'll change my mind
so you just mentioned testable code and
this is also in your book and topic that
comes up so what is testable what makes
code testable mmm love that query that
question actually and this is something
again
speaking of recurring learning curves
and patterns as the consultant working
with a software quality this is what I
hear a lot our code is not testable and
one like sub-objective of my book is to
actually teach some nomenclature testing
nomenclature where testable is actually
one of the words you need to know and if
you just Google a testable you will find
and I don't think people do that often
enough you will find that testable is
code that's observable and controllable
so and and I love that that's the school
book definition and it's actually a very
powerful definition I would say in the
book I chose to add code that's small
and smallness as a property so can we
can we zoom in about on those two words
a bit
because I'm not sure everyone
understands what exactly they mean I
don't really understand what what is
observable really mean what is
controllable yes and you explain a bit
yes so these are properties that apply
at all levels for example if you if you
complain about your unit tests a very
common pattern of failure with unit
tests is for example that your unit test
does things that a unit test is not
supposed to do it reads something from a
file system it expects something to
happen on the network stuff like that
these are things you don't always
control your file system may be
structured differently your test server
may may not be responding stuff like
that and as soon lose that your test
your code becomes untestable yeah and
this this scales that that's the beauty
of it if you scale that is that
something unit test level and again now
I could carry carried away here but I'm
just going to slow down it scales
because if you look at systems for
example an entire system may be
untestable because of external
dependencies that you simply can't
control a practical example of this
where I really encountered this is I
used to work with testing a logics for
buying or selling stocks and the only
sort of realistic testing environment
available was actually a public
environment where many different actors
were able to do did their transaction it
was like life day now yes
live data so so there was no way for
example and there were reasons if time
permits I can we can sort of dive into
the reasons why we didn't stop this
environment out but there were there
were reasons for really keeping this
environment but basically if we put an
order we wanted to buy ourselves
something someone else snatched that
order and that that happened on on the
system level so here we had obviously we
we had observability because we were
able
to query the system we we could see that
our order is no longer there but we
didn't control wrong yeah and this is
mean the profound thing is here that
it's games that were all across all
layers and it starts at the unit level
and skills up to two system levels so
control abilities obviously being able
to set things in a certain state an
enemy of controllability is often the
database people seldom take the time to
and the painful process of actually
setting up their database and setting up
whatever layer they need to populate
database with certain test data that I
mean that's that's that's the poster
child for controllability and yes
so you mentioned the outside role a lot
like life data and a database but are
they also properties of the source code
itself that make code investable yes
there are a few but again the thing is
that they are actually falling into
these are the big these are the big
groups so if you just keep these in mind
you're probably gonna be fine but what
if you break this down on like a more
manageable level obviously things that
will affect your both observability and
controllability are indirect input and
output yeah and simply what these things
are is because again this is so so calm
on how to deal with indirect input and
output and I'd say first step one is to
understand what that is to be sort of
named the devil first so what isn't it
right there so output is direct input
and our output are direct if they're
observable through the public interface
you send something to a method routine
function call it whatever you like you
get a result back so that's obviously
direct inputs and what you get back is
direct output if all your code were
structured like this you would have you
wouldn't call it untestable yes because
everything you can see everything
however as soon as your routine becomes
kind of a black box and it starts
creating it's as simple as actually as
creating other let's call them objects
here or entities or so start creating
things it starts reading something again
from a database obviously that's in the
read input it starts sending stuff it
could be as simple as printing I mean
your your hello world program has
indirect output actually so your hello
world program is actually it's it's
actually harder it's to test but these
are scenarios that all developers
encounter yes you have to print we do
have yes read from the database what do
we do Alexandre how buzz how do we test
that type of things again first the key
success factor is to name it if I can
name it you will know that this is where
were your different kinds of test
doubles enter the scene and basically
does there's a mapping it's more or less
one one-to-one mapping between type of
test double and your problems of
indirect and direct input so stubs a
stub is the test double the sole purpose
of which is to provide indirect input I
mean that is the the purpose of a stub a
mark object the purpose of a mark object
is to verify indirect output so it's
actually if we can name stuff we have
the test doubles that's a solved problem
okay that makes sense thank you so your
book doesn't only cover unit testing you
go a lot deeper you have you talked
about more rich techniques that are
available to developers and one of those
techniques that you mentioned is
idea of designed by contract which is a
relatively old idea already has
advocated for example by Bertrand Meyer
Eiffel so for those listeners not
familiar with that contest what is
programming by contract programming by
contract is okay so you first of all the
design by contract and programming by
contract thing when I did the research
for for the book I actually wanted to to
call it design my contract that's the
name it's it's known under however that
particular thing is trademarked so I
needed to put yes I need it that's why I
had to to put programming my contract
and basically what programming or design
by contract is it's about formalizing
responsibilities you're saying that a
class says the definition and it's
collaborators they have a relationship
there are obligations and there there
are benefits so you formalize a
relationship between two program
elements I like that word program
element is a fantastic word so it's
about formalizing the relationship and
the program elements can be methods or
classes or api's it's it's more it's
more about I think it's easier the
easiest case is really the the method
the the I API level is a there are
variations but that's that's the easiest
case so why isn't designed by contract
really mainstream it's it's an old idea
and it does seem like a very good idea
and make it very clear document what the
responsibilities are yet it doesn't
really happen in practice
why do you reckon that is mmm I wish I
knew
I do have some theories I want to hear
you so one theory is that probably it
touches a little it may feel a little
too too much like formal methods
it feels very formal it feels document
II yeah it doesn't feel like program
yeah you need to you need to stop and
think that's bad you can't back on your
keyboard you stop stop at the G so
that's one thing and the other thing is
that the construct supporting it they're
not really primary citizens in in the
languages in the popular languages
things like preconditions post
conditions yes yes exactly so and I mean
in iPhone where where these things are
actually built into the language they
read very well they're very explicit
unfortunately I I fell if you look at
the common these indexes for programming
language popularity Thai obey index and
they pew pew IPL in exist I think iPhone
is somewhat below yeah 0.1 83 percent 7
so if we want to do this on by contract
in more traditional or more mainstream
languages Java you know do you need
libraries or frameworks for that every
language has the or well I should be
careful about saying every but the
majority striking majority of languages
has the assert keyword which is like the
standard thing for enforcing pre and
post conditions there are libraries for
contracts for both Java and.net
environments and obviously other
environments as well the way I think
about programming by contract in the
kink in the context of developer testing
is that I don't really think to me
the essence is actually the mindset the
mindset of the terror there is a
formalized responsibility between two
program elements or two and two things
and that formalizing this responsibility
will help you to answer the question how
many tests do I need to write okay so
it's not that I was putting there
putting the formal responsibility in the
source code per se it's more about
thinking about the responsibilities and
then you have them in your mind and
they're part of the shared understanding
of the source code which is then
supported by the tool yes because
there's a yes because there's there are
different ways to actually enforce
contracts again in Iife of the
traditional way is runtime verification
you can partly enforce contracts by
static analysis actually you can do that
and I'd argue that unit testing is
actually again a way of enforcing
contracts because it's really again the
contract is assessed is an abstract
construct so there are different levels
but to me at least to me it's proven
most valuable to just have this as an
idea to generate test cases tests
because there are again returning to
this learning curve a very common
question is how many tests do I need to
write like like like it reads on testing
yes exactly like if it's quantifiable
but this is one angle to it there are
other angles to it but this is this is
one thing that will help you determine
the number of tests right so is this
worth it for all type of projects or
does your source code need specific
characteristics for new to be for it to
be worth it to invest in design my
contracts again dependent depending on
what you what you would actually put in
the definition of investing into
programming by contract I mean as soon
as you've got one thing calling the
other you have a contract it's just a
matter of is there
implicit or explicit yes and putting
tools putting invariants around that
thing or may not be worth it especially
if you're in an environment that doesn't
do this traditionally however stopping
and thinking about this it's always
worth it I mean you you need to be
explicit about your interaction yeah so
to again in notes of the points that
we've been talking about it is about
writing down or at least understanding
what the expectations of the source code
are I think we can we can summarize it
like that yeah so something else you
talked about in your book which is
related I think it's specification based
testing so this is about writing down
the expectations even more formally
right
what are you consider to be specific
specification based testing so the word
I'm using a specification based testing
technique techniques and it's very
undramatic this is again a very Google
whole word which you will find in your
basic test or exam what's sort of
important about specific specification
based testing is that this is one of
these these things that didn't make it
to the to the developer books and blah
yes it mainstream yes yes yes it's been
confined to to the testing world it's
never bare or at least in my mind it's
never been made popular enough among
developers I agree I go to lots of
conference and I don't think I've seen
lots of talks about specification based
testing or designed by Gandhi right and
in recent times but the thing is but
there is a good reason for that -
because it's like extremely I'm sexy
actually I mean his specification the
only thing is specification based test
techniques and actually I don't even
call it by that name I just call them
fundamental testing techniques it's the
the testing 101 techniques for testers
and the core specification based
techniques because they can be derived
from the specification if you you have
your user story or you have
a formal document or or a wish list or
whatever you can study this and you can
derive tests like how do you do that
suppose I have a user story right in
front of me and I want to derive test
from it
what do I do so I shake the paper until
the tests come out the thing is let me
just explain the things I put into
specification yes
so the does again as I said very unsexy
its equivalents partitioning is a
boundary value analysis is state
transition testing it's basically
different types of truth tables so can
you give an example of one of those sure
normally I'm gonna give you just a
schoolbook example let's say you've got
whatever numerical input the classical
thing people under a certain age may not
engage in certain transactions or
whatever and you have you have an age
check so a boundary value analysis or
let's start with equivalence
partitioning obviously in that
particular case you may have two two
partitions of data because if you enter
your age you you obviously gonna be in
the valid part of this interval and
you'll obviously be in the invalid that
part you will be younger than let's say
18 or 20 so that that could be two
partitions there could be more there
could be more where you actually send
incomplete garbage into this you could
treat this as a separate partition the
important thing is not really how you
slice these partitions is the important
thing is that you're aware of their
existence now in between these
partitions this is usually where bugs
lurk I mean it's so easy to if you have
your age check it's so easy to omit the
character or something and you you have
and you're not to be you know you want
people to hit the interval correctly so
this is it's like smaller than or
smaller or equal that's it
type of things yes yes that's what I was
envisioning and so this is where
boundary value analysis comes in is that
you know your partitions and you know
that I need to pay more attention to the
boundaries so you will obviously test
more at the boundaries related to this
is obviously different heuristics for
certain values that may or may not be
around the boundaries of different
partitions but you may want to look you
may want to examine them more closely
anyway anyway and these are things like
empty arrays collections stuff that's
that's empty yes I was more thinking
about no secretely edge case yes like
knows empty empty collection empty
strings
yes Nan's not number kind of stuff and
this heuristics that peculiar sticks for
testing is one zero many which is
applicable again for at the unitest
level so so these are this is boundary
value analysis and and equivalence
partitioning state transition testing
basically is about modeling your if
certain types of software will really be
best modulus as state machines and if
you sort of go through the hassle of
some of modeling this you can either do
this graphically or either do this
formally or just write it down on a
whiteboard but really visualize the
states and the transitions and derive
test cases from that and obviously
you've got the table a different
decision table kind of stuff again is to
just visualize all the inputs and and
outputs and outcomes and from these
techniques if you apply them
consistently consistently this is where
your magic if you shake your your video
your little index card or at least if
you shake something which you've
produced you is using these exist your
test cases will flow so all of these
techniques
we can catch under the umbrella of
helping you to come up with new test
case yes
this relates your thing to what you said
in the beginning of the podcast and many
books about testing and are about how to
execute tests how to run tests but not
about how am i how do I know what I'm
going to test and these are all ways to
help you think of what are the
responsibilities of my model what
exactly what are the states that my
thing can be in to help you think about
new test case is that correct I would
phrase it slightly differently you are
the expert I would say that again this
is so super basic is that you you don't
even speak of this anymore you as you
said before you will not see these
topics on a testing conference because
that's like below 101 it's below 101
however the crux is that it's below 101
for people who have a testing training
it's not below 101 for for developers I
was writing ringing these things to
developers I mean these are things if
you are a super novice testers these are
things you will try first
however these things are also manual
they repeatable they don't really
require any creativity because they are
so well formalized you know if you of
course you can actually argue over your
different partitions it's not always
easy to partition stuff for example it's
not obvious how to partition but most of
the time it kind of is so as a developer
if you just aware of all of this you
know what to put in your in your test
kit in your developer test and that
partly also helps you to mitigate this
creator bias because at least you have
certain ground rules I need to I will
use these techniques and I will base my
test cases on these techniques and then
I've got all of this covered
then comes somebody who's an expert in
testing and trusts trust you to have put
all this verifiable this that person
do some some sampling but that person
will be able to do something yeah and
also it gives you a shared vocabulary
because now access sir can ask me as a
developer what partitions did you
consider or they can say did you think
of the state machine did you write you
down or how many states do you have and
that makes it easier to communicate with
you yes and thank you for bringing this
up because I that's also so important
about that's actually again I've got
this all these sub goals with I book and
just I mean I dedicated an entire
chapter just to the vocabulary to
facilitate color communication and
collaboration so thanks for bringing
this up so I want to talk about two more
controversial topics if you're still
with me yes one is test coverage all
right should we care about test coverage
is this something you should care about
it developer is this something you
should care about as a tester or is this
an entire known issue and you should
just test until you feel you've tested
your system well enough or is there a
number we should go for okay there's a
number you should go for okay so all the
best projects that's I'm gonna start
with the anecdote on the best projects
where we've actually employed developer
testing test coverage was never an issue
because if you write your unit tests or
if you do that test-driven development
and you write your integration tests
your coverage will be above 90%
automatically so when doing developer
testing coverage is actually non-issue
however the issue with coverage is of
course that it doesn't really tell you
anything about correctness it just tells
you that one piece of code has executed
another piece of code so I think these
are the lines along which I user usually
reasoning so it tells you for example
coverage tells you that your code is
testable you are able to write another
one routine that is able to test another
routine that's good
so obviously a coverage shouldn't be
dropping personally I like high coverage
because because of that because it tells
you code is testable somebody has made
an effort to call your code to exercise
your code however it will not tell you
about the quality of your of your
testing yeah so it says something about
internal quality but not necessarily
about external quality yes that's it
very these are good label stupid to put
on this yes so aiming for a number again
I think it should be a rising trend but
just if aim for a number you need to
know why you're aiming for this number
just saying we need fifty fifty percent
or something is not really in my mind
solving any problems okay second comes
rehearsal so make a test first or test
last should you write to unit test
before you program or first programming
then the test or it doesn't matter or it
can be mixed what's your take on this
okay so first of all I've been not
slavish ly but I've been following this
debate it's been going on forever and I
to be honest I I think I've stopped
following it a while ago but I'm sort of
resuming it different conferences and so
I try to be familiar with it
what's one thing that in this debate
that has happened is actually I think we
lost the just the notion of unit testing
it's either you do TDD or you do not
don't do TDD and if you do TDD you're
good if you don't TDD you pad we've sort
of lost a little just okay I'm not to me
TDD I was super duper expert in unit
testing am i okay
so we've lost that that at least to me
that dimension has been lost so the
debate this is slightly one-sided it's
do TDD not not do TDD
my take on this is that testability is a
function of controllability
observability
smallness and it's not a function of
time and presidents so the so in a way
to novice developers test driven
development sort of Kairos through the
promise if you do this first then
something magic will happen being a
little meaner but but so so that that's
from the testability point of view so
there's no nothing magic about
test-driven development
that being said writing your tests first
will obviously ensure that you reach
these goals I mean you need to if you
start with a test you will obviously
reach controllability and observability
by definition because otherwise there's
no way you will be able to write code
that lumic then has passed so it's it's
a fantastic way of reaching these these
properties and smaller also because
actually TDD tells you not to - it will
die it will prohibit you from adding
extra extra code and stuff like that so
you will reach all the properties of
testability doing TDD however it's just
that if you know these properties there
are other ways of reaching them so I
think what you're saying is that test
first is a good strategy if you're just
starting with this if you're starting
with writing test but after a while you
get used to it and then it doesn't
really matter anymore when well there's
another dimension to this actually and
it is III I think that's overall the the
biggest challenge with doing TDD is that
it requires you to be able to first
visualize what you're actually going to
do and how it needs you need it requires
to visualize how you're going to test it
often you work with them stack or
technology that you're not really
familiar with you're working in a system
you're not really familiar with it's got
all sort of side effects and quirks
going on and sometimes you really need
to just prototype your way
through different layers and in these
situations TDD is really really
unhelpful so that's the other dimensions
so it has to do with controllable it has
to do with how much do you know about
this yes knowledge about the system the
domain and the problem actually
sometimes you really just need to go
crazy and try things out so what I do in
these cases is that there's no testing
whatsoever there's no there's no unit
test at all however as soon as and I
think I do this even subconsciously as
soon as I've got sort of a clear idea of
okay it's probably gonna go in that
direction I think I'm actually reverting
to the TDD then those are of course
different types of TDD and there's
different rigidness about TDD the TDI
present in my book is not as rigid as
the classical yes
so my I'd like to put the label
pragmatic on my TDD obviously that tests
are written firsts but know that they're
written first in the book the written
first it's just that for example in the
classic book on TDD Kent Beck uses the
refactoring stage to really remove the
plication whereas I use my refactoring
to really like get rid of ugly code
sometimes I get rid of duplication
sometimes not sometimes like it reads
something else and sometimes I end up in
situations where I really need to I have
sort of done by refactoring but I'm
looking ahead and okay I need to
refactor again so it's I am cheating a
little maybe I don't know but I like the
label pragmatic it's a good basically
DVD test first is a good idea but it
isn't always practical so being somewhat
pragmatic about it I think it's a good
idea so that's more or less of the time
we have of course we will link to your
book if people want to know more are
there other resources where people can
read from you
yes there are actually there's the book
companion site which is developer
testing that rocks
I actually developer testing that come
was taken as so i registered rocks now
that's a on going project so stuff is
being added as I go I don't have an
infinite amount of time but I'm trying
to put a little tidbit here in there si
I have time so that's that I think
that's that's where stuff is going to
hang okay so we will put that in the
show now it's according and along with a
link to your book thanks for being on
the show thank you for having me
[Music]
thanks for listening to se radio an
educational program brought to you by I
Triple E software magazine for more
information about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at SE -
radioman to provide feedback you can
write comments on each episode on the
website or write a review on itunes
mention a message us on twitter at se
radio or search for the software
engineering radio group on LinkedIn
Google+ or Facebook you can also email
us at team at se - radio net this and
all other episodes of SU radio is
licensed under the creative commons 2.5
license thanks again for your support
[Music]
you